Before we take a look at how osmosis and tonicity affect
a cell, let’s review what each of these terms means.
Osmosis represents the diffusion of water across a semi-permeable
membrane.
The term tonicity refers to the relative solute concentration
of two environments separated by a semipermeable membrane.
In other words, by comparing the tonicity of the solution,
you can determine the direction in which osmosis will occur.
To demonstrate how tonicity affects a cell,
let’s place some red blood cells into a beaker containing pure water.
In this case, the solute concentration is greater inside
the cells, than in the surrounding water.  In other words,
the contents of the cells are hypertonic in relation to the hypotonic
contents of the beaker.  Because of this, osmotic
pressure results in the diffusion of water across the membrane and into the
cells.  Over time, if enough water enters the cells,
the cell membranes may burst.  This is called lysis.
Now lets place the red blood cells in a beaker containing a solution
of salt, such as sodium chloride.  Since the contents of the beaker
beaker are hypertonic in relation to the interior of the cell,
the water within the cell will diffuse across the membrane and into the
contents of the beaker.  This causes crenation or shrinking of
the cells.
If the red blood cells are placed in a beaker whose contents
match the tonicity within the cells, then there is no net gain
or loss of water.  The environments within the beaker
and inside the cells are said to be isotonic, or the same.
An important thing to remember, is that osmotic pressure
always causes water to move from a hypotonic environment toward
a hypertonic environment.  In other words, water moves toward
areas of high salt or sugar concentrations.  This simple
process is used to drive the operation of our kidneys and explains
some of the physiological consequences of diseases such as diabetes.